《斯巴达克斯：血与沙》
《斩尽杀绝》
看着他们
Mind them.
尊贵的Batiatus家族 一直谦虚恭谨!
The noble House of Batiatus stands humbled!
哪怕有诸神的眷顾
Humbled by the blessings
也始终谨言慎行
the gods have seen fit to shower upon us.
卡普亚最尊贵的市民们
And by the presence of the most revered citizens
欢迎你们的到来
in all of Capua,
让我们共庆Claudius Glaber副将
come to join in celebrating the patronage
对我们的资助!
of Legatus Claudius Glaber!
副将因议院事务繁重 无法出席
The man himself regrets the duties of the Senate
对此 他表示遗憾
prevent his attendance,
但他已经将想要说的话 罗列成稿
but he would see us properly addressed,
并请他挚爱的妻子
his words delivered
向我们转述
by pleasing tongue of trusted wife.
各位亲爱的卡普亚市民
Good citizens of Rome's favored sister.
很高兴
It is with great pleasure that
由我 Claudius Glaber副将
I, Legatus Claudius Glaber, bestow upon
向Quintus Lentulus Batiatus
Quintus Lentulus Batiatus
给予资助
my patronage,
及其它附加利益
and all encompassing benefits.
卡普亚上下 再无他人
No man in all of Capua is more deserving
能享有如此尊贵的特权
of such esteemed privilege.
在这座连遭变故的城市
Good Batiatus should be held as example
Batiatus应成为全市楷模
to a city mired in shadows and treachery.
用他的良善之心 为我们带来光明
The guiding light of his virtuous heart
指引大家驱散黑暗和烦恼
providing illumination in these dark and troubling times.
基于此 以及其它数不胜数的原因...
For this reason and too many others to give voice...
别轻举妄动
Still yourself.
我将无条件地全权支持他
I lend my full and unconditional support
迈向高贵的市政官之席
to the honored position of Aedile.
Aemilia可没说过你有意参政
Aemilia failed to mention you had mind towards office.
哦 Sextus 我承认
Oh, I admit to none, good Sextus.
在副将提议之前 我的确没这想法
Until the Legatus broached the subject.
市政官仅次于行政官
Aedile is but a breath below Magistrate.
嗯
Um.
我们吃饭去吧 边吃边聊
We should dine, and discuss the matter further.
Glaber副将和他的支持 令我激动万分
My heart to Legatus Glaber and his support.
我希望大家也能和我同享喜悦
In the hopes that you will share it in the coming days,
特呈上鲜血之礼!
I present a gift of blood!
竞技场的两位传奇人物
Two legends of the arena,
将在终极决斗中 一决高下!
to face each other sine missione!
不谈宽恕!
No quarter given!
不讲仁慈!
No mercy shown!
请看 Crixus!
Behold, Crixus!
凶残的高卢人!
The savage Gaul!
试问 有谁能与之匹敌呢?
And who shall attempt to tame him?
只此一人
There can be but one man.
斯巴达克斯!
Spartacus!
死亡之影的屠灭者!
Slayer of the Shadow of Death!
他真是无与伦比 对吧?
He is of a form, is he not?
他是神祇的化身
He stands a god.
Crixus啊...
Crixus...
我给过答复了
I have given my answer.
打完这场再说
Let us finish this.
开始!
Begin!
(2天前)
你在玩火
You speak of dangerous things.
我们本来就活在水深火热之中
We live in dangerous times.
许多人仍认为 Crixus才是我们真正的战神
Many yet hold Crixus our true Champion.
我也这么想
Count me among them.
Doctore啊
Doctore.
我请求进行木桩练习
I would work the palus.
斯巴达克斯的请求 我批准了
Permission for Spartacus.
你和Hamilcar商量过么?
Have you traded words with Hamilcar?
他站在我们这边
He is with us.
但只要Crixus不表态
But Castus and the other Gauls
Castus和其他高卢人
refuse to grab cock without
也会不吱声
Crixus holding their balls.
Rhaskos站在哪一边?
Where does Rhaskos stand?
和他们一样
The same.
我们的人不多
Our numbers are yet shallow.
我们必须获得Crixus的支持
We must gain Crixus' support
使队伍壮大起来
and see them rise.
可那家伙仍然被关着呢
The fucking mad man's still under lock and key.
如果不能跟他说话
How will you turn him to cause
又怎能让他同意起义?
if you cannot break words with him?
战神是有特权的
Being champion yet affords privilege.
我们可以利用这一点
A way shall present itself.
说话啊!
Answer!
最好能快点儿"利用"起来
It best "present" fucking soon.
我说过要你站着吧?
Did I tell you to stand?
Glaber同意资助了
Glaber falls to patronage,
那些名门望族 纷纷以我
and the men of influence greet me
马首是瞻!
as a fucking brother!
辉煌的一天
A day of shining glory.
转眼即被乌云破坏
Marred by darkening cloud.
主人 我有话想跟您说
I beg a word, Dominus.
私下谈谈吧
In private.
Doctore啊
Doctore,
别忧心忡忡
well spill sour thoughts,
看事情 要看到好的一面
and hear them sweetened.
Glaber的雇佣兵 对人无故鞭打
Glaber's mercenaries punish absent cause.
大家都苦不堪言
The men suffer at their hand.
必须把这口气咽下去
It is a burden that must be endured
我没时间去管这种琐事
I have no time for such petty concerns.
恕我直言 每个训练场都需要
With respect, every ludus requires
角斗士主人给予高度重视
the attention of its lanista.
我要力争上游 站到比竞技场更高的地方
I seek a loftier title, one far removed from the arena.
您想让家族传统成为历史?
You would see your family's heritage a thing of memory?
不
No.
我只是厌倦了尘土和单调
Yet I tire of the dust and drudgery,
我想找个更合适的人来接替我
and I would have my interests in blood and sand
继续将角斗士事业发扬光大
overseen by someone with more attentive eyes.
他必须一个永远忠诚的人
Someone who has forever proven loyal.
您想把训练场 委托给一个奴隶?
You would entrust the ludus to a slave?
他不再是奴隶了
A slave, never.
我本打算留到庆典来宣布的
I had thought to make announcement at the celebration,
但你既然问了 我就告诉你吧
but you force my hand.
我在拟定文书 打算赐你自由
My advocate is drawing up papers granting your freedom.
自由?
Freedom?
你不再是我的Doctore
No longer shall you be my Doctore.
你将成为训练场主人
You will assume the mantle of lanista,
并可以使用自己的本名
and be warmly greeted by your name,
即Oenomaus
Oenomaus.
我以为你会为此感到高兴
I had thought the news to please.
抱歉
Apologies,
我听到一个传言
I have heard rumor.
令我寝食难安
One that has vexed sleep.
说吧 说出来就又能安睡了
Well give voice, and dream again.
我听说 Barca没有获得自由
Barca was not granted freedom.
而是被你所杀
Instead he met his end, at your hands.
这个传言确有其事
The rumor is true.
却没交代清楚理由
Yet absent reasoning.
我派Barca去给Ovidius
Barca was dispatched to deliver
送个口信而已
a simple message to Ovidius.
他却杀了Ovidius和他全家
Instead he slaughtered the man and his entire fucking family,
简直目无法纪
against command.
在行政官发现真相
I had no choice but to take his life,
并把我们赶尽杀绝之前
before the Magistrate discovered the deed
我无路可选 只能杀了他
and pulled us all to ruin.
那Ashur呢?
And Ashur?
他是否对该"选择"贡献颇多?
Did he aid in this "choice"?
等你成了角斗士主人
When you are lanista,
你也会有面对这种
you shall also be faced with decisions
两难抉择的时候
grave of consequence.
到时你就知道 什么叫两害相权取其轻
And know your measure by how your blade falls.
你能感觉到他蠢蠢欲动
Can you yet feel him move,
迫不及待地 想出来见见世面么?
eager to make entrance into the world?
你怎么知道是个男孩?
How do you divine a boy?
因为天神眷顾我们啊
Because the gods fucking favor us.
Glaber的资助
Glaber's patronage,
让我有望迈入卡普亚最高阶层
access to the upper strata of Capua,
成为政坛人物
the promise of political office.
我们的付出
Everything we have bled for,
终于有了回报
finally within our grasp.
我们是真正受上天眷顾的人
We are truly blessed.
我今天宣布的消息 多么振奋人心
I deliver but glorious news this day,
可你却不愠不火!
to be met with tempered response!
别高兴过头 还有庆典在等着我们呢
Joy is restrained to lend clear mind to celebration.
Glaber的资助 或许能为我们平步青云铺平道路
Glaber's patronage may have paved road to the elite,
但那些上层人士的胃口可不小
but they are of ravenous appetite.
那你打算拿什么
And what meal would you suggest
去喂饱他们?
to see them sated?
Batiatus家族唯一能提供的东西
One that only the House of Batiatus can prepare.
让死亡之影的屠灭者 斯巴达克斯
Spartacus, Slayer of Theokoles,
来一场死亡角逐赛
in a contest to the death.
我们已经在Numerius的成年礼上
We have already presented such diversion
办过此类活动了
at Numerius' Toga Virilis.
Varro根本不配和卡普亚战神比试
Varro was no match for the Champion of Capua.
我们必须让他们看看 当晚没有出现的胜景
We must give them what was denied that night.
全卡普亚都翘首以待的
What all of Capua longs to see,
但只有我们这儿少数人有幸
but only a privileged few under our roof
得以见到的胜景
may bear witness to.
卡普亚战神
The Champion of Capua,
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus in a fight for his life
与唯一屡战屡胜他的勇士 来场生死大对决
against the only man who has ever defeated him.
这就是你的期望?
Is this your fucking hope?
让那个败落的高卢人有机会
That the fallen Gaul is granted opportunity
卷土重来?
to regain position?
出去
Out.
你误会我了
You mistake intent.
我要见到Crixus
I would see Crixus dead,
为冒犯Batiatus家族
for offenses committed
付出生命的代价
against the House of Batiatus.
在这点上 我们的立场倒是一致
Then we stand as one in such regard.
你的话 尚令我无法相信
Oh your tongue named cause of doubt.
Crixus是唯一对斯巴达克斯 造成威胁的角斗士
Crixus is the only gladiator to pose threat to Spartacus.
当我竞选参政的时候
And there is yet political advantage
亮出"送雨的使者"这张王牌
to parading the Bringer of Rain
对我的政治生涯 将大为有利啊
as I campaign for office.
那我们一定要确保斯巴达克斯获胜
Then we must ensure Spartacus victorious.
则Crixus将被永远忘却
And Crixus fades from memory.
好了 你们退下吧
That will be all.
有了资助 束缚也随之而来
Patronage comes with unfortunate attachment.
我深有体会
A fact I am well aware of.
你最初的模样 仿佛还历历在目
I am reminded of the first time you stood before me
那时你是个野人 戴着镣铐
in this office, a savage in chains.
现在你却直面死亡 毫无畏惧
Now you stand as death, made meat and bone.
是你把我历练至此
It was your hand that forged my purpose.
然而Batiatus家族如此兴旺
Yet it is upon your shoulders
并将继续光耀万世
the House of Batiatus has been so elevated,
全是你的功劳
and continues to rise.
两天之后 我们将举办卡普亚最具影响力的盛事
Two days hence we play host to the most influential in Capua,
庆祝成功得到资助
in celebration of patronage.
尽管大家来参加庆典 是为了近身一睹
Although a closer look at the Slayer of Theokoles
死亡之影屠灭者的风采
be the true draw.
我非常荣幸
A great honor.
其他角斗士也能一同出现在庄园内吗?
Will the men be displayed in the villa?
副将会对此表示不悦
The Legatus would frown upon such storied tradition.
你和其他人的活动范围 将限定于广场
You and the others will be confined to the square.
我们的客人在哪里观赏呢?
And how will our guests have view?
购买露台观看
From purchase of the balcony.
没人能抵御
No eye will be denied
卡普亚战神的英姿!
the Champion of Capua!
他将直面旗鼓相当的对手 浴血奋战!
As he faces his arch enemy in a match to the death!
我要和Crixus对阵?
I am to fight Crixus?
你担心吗?
This concerns you?
不 我期待已久了
It is long overdue.
但杀掉困兽一般软弱的人
Yet there is no honor
毫无荣耀可言
in taking the life of a caged lion.
我希望他早日恢复训练
I would see him return to training,
这样观众看他死亡才过瘾
so he may better thrill the crowd before his end.
你想得真周全
You truly have fucking mind for this.
Crixus该被放回去了 可只是为了接受训练而已
Crixus shall be freed from bond yet only for training.
我不会任由这禽兽为所欲为
I would not have the animal run free,
以免他再次狂性大发
lest he again bares teeth.
快去休息吧
Remove yourself to slumber,
有梦才能成真
and dreams of extracting them.
对不起 主人
Apologies, Dominus.
与睡眠相比 我更需要...
There is something I crave more than sleep...
你所求之事 绝对办不到
You ask the impossible.
在我去见Batiatus之前
The gates to the villa must stand open
庄园的门得一直开着
before I make a move on Batiatus.
你要让我独自涉险啊
You would have me risk all.
为了什么?
And for what?
为了让斯达巴克斯报仇?
So that Spartacus may have his revenge?
不
No.
这样他的内心就会恢复平静了
So that his heart might find a measure of peace.
她是这样的女人吗
Was she such a woman,
我说你的妻子
your wife.
她是我心中的太阳
She was the sun.
却已经陨落
Never to rise again.
要否认她能温暖人心
A heavy thing,
实属不易
to be denied its warmth.
我会确保届时大门敞开
I will see the gate opened.
但我有个条件...
But I would have exchange...
我的条件是
This is my price.
与我交欢
To feel you inside me.
我多想感受到一丝 你对她炙热的爱恋...
To know pale shadow of the love that you felt for her...
我才不会把赌注压在高卢人身上
I would not have wagered the Gaul
他对斯巴达克斯根本不成威胁!
such a challenge to Spartacus!
你小看他了 Aemilia
You underestimate the man, Aemilia.
Crixus是昔日的战神 不是吗?
Crixus was once Champion, was he not?
这场比赛才刚刚开始
The match is but newly born.
我们都难以预测结果
Much may yet happen as it matures.
抱歉 主人
Apologies, Domina.
我得去商店再买些酒
I must gather more wine from the stores.
让别人去吧
Send another.
你要伴我左右 招待宾客
I would keep you close, to attend the guests.
听我说...
You must listen to me...
(1天前)
主人要放我出去了吗?
Dominus has ordered my release?
是斯巴达克斯求他的
It was Spartacus that moved his hand.
斯巴达克斯?
Spartacus?
他希望你在与他对战之时...
He desires you at your best...
处于最佳状态
when you stand before him sine missione.
众神终于显灵了
The gods finally answer my prayers.
要是早点显灵就好了
Had they but answered sooner.
明天 在太阳落山时
You stand before him tomorrow,
你与他一战
as the sun fades.
就算此时交战
If it were this very moment,
结果也是一样
the outcome would not change.
我对Naevia许过诺
I have made promise to Naevia.
在获取自由之前 我不会死的
I will not die until I have gained my freedom,
她会重回我的怀抱
and she is in my arms again.
我们先别说自由的事了
Delay talk of freedom,
等有望自由时 再谈不迟
until there are ears that would welcome the sound.
我怕主人不愿给我自由啊
I fear Dominus shall forever be deaf to it.
要有信念
Place your faith to closer quarters.
主人使我摆脱了劳役之苦
Dominus releases me from the bonds of servitude,
让我荣登角斗士主人之位
to assume mantle as lanista.
你实至名归
It is a title well deserved.
让我们携手 使这训练场重返辉煌...
Together we will restore honor to this ludus...
让Naevia与你团聚
and Naevia to your arms.
斯巴达克斯阻碍了你
Spartacus but stands in your way.
那就把他打倒
Then he shall fall.
举行庆典?
A celebration?
届时精英汇聚
Filled with the elite.
杀了他们 卡普亚就乱套了
Their deaths will shatter Capua to chaos.
等他们回过神来追我们
It'll be days before they regain senses
都过去好几天了
to pursue us.
我们的计划成型了
Our plan takes form.
那Crixus怎么办?
What of Crixus?
你还是得想办法 和那该死的高卢人
You still must find way to broach subject
谈谈这个问题
with the fucking Gaul.
会有办法的 我保证
It presents itself, as promised.
耶!
Yeah!
Crixus啊
Crixus.
耶!
Yeah!
我操
Fuck my ass.
万事俱备 只欠让你的宿敌
Now all that remains is convincing
加入到我们的队伍中来了
a man that hates you to join your cause.
我该做的都做完了吧?
You have seen task to completion?
我丈夫的资助使你们
My husband's patronage has lifted
平步青云啊
your celebration beyond the heavens,
上层名流 全聚于此庆典
clouds bursting with honored guests.
Altius和他的侄子Gaius吗?
Altius and his cousin Gaius?
他们是一定要来的...
They are a necessity...
按你们所吩咐的 也会来的
and are delivered, as commanded.
Aemilia的丈夫 Sextus呢?
Aemilia's husband, Sextus?
他虽已不是行政官
He's a former magistrate,
可仍旧声望很高
yet beloved by many.
获取他的支持 对我们进军政坛至关重要
His support would all but secure office.
他去罗马有要事
Pressing affairs draw him to Rome.
这可不妙啊 Ilithyia
That does not bring comfort Ilithyia.
如果他出席的话 你就宽心了吧
Then perhaps his attendance shall.
他会推迟启程
He will delay travel,
只为来参加你的庆典
with mind towards your celebration.
你是怎样让他改变主意的呢?
How did you turn his attentions?
他青睐于我
He favors me.
大多数身为人夫者 都垂涎于我
Most husbands do.
很感谢你的帮助
Your services have been deeply appreciated.
可仍有一事相求
Yet more is needed.
你尊敬的丈夫没有出席
In the absence of your honored husband,
所以请你代替我们这位最尊贵的客人
we would have you address
作简短致辞
our most noble guests.
只需以他的角度
Just a few words as if fallen from his mouth,
称颂Batiatus家族的美德即可
extolling the virtues of the House of Batiatus.
我会好好构思
I shall compose something appropriate
该如何致辞
for the occasion.
不用了
No need.
我已经为你写好了
I've already seen to it.
我不仅行动受限
My hands are no longer my own
如今你连我说什么都要操纵吗?
and now you seize my fucking tongue?
我可不想让你说些不着边际的话
I would not have it flap about, absent direction.
你对我的侮辱 什么时候是个头呢?
How much longer must I suffer your indignities?
只要我还有一口气 你就躲不了
While breath gives life to my command.
那就如你所愿吧
As you wish, then.
我知道我们之间关系一度紧张
I know there have been tensions between us.
可我们如今何必给双方
Yet I see no cause for our current arrangement
带来不快呢
to fall into unpleasantness.
我们曾是那么亲近的朋友
We were such dear friends once.
你不想重塑我们的友谊吗?
Would you not see it so again?
若我能扭转乾坤
Would that I had power to reverse the sun,
使世界恢复原样 我就与你和好
and restore the world to its proper place.
稍事休息
Rest.
去吃饭吧
Eat.
正午过后 我们再开始训练
We resume after midday sun has past.
你动作很敏捷嘛
You move well.
就像没被鞭打过一样
As if lash had never struck.
把痛苦转嫁给别人之后 自己就没事了
Pain is erased, when inflicted upon others.
希望在我们交战之时
I would have you at your best
你出于最佳状态
when we face each other.
这是你全部的愿望吗?
Is that all you'd have from me?
Rhasko和我提起了你的愿望
Rhasko speaks of your desires.
你是不脑子缺根弦啊
What fever grips brain,
我怎么可能和你一个鼻孔出气呢?
that Spartacus would think me to band with him?
而使我的勇士们命悬一线?
To risk the lives of my men?
还有我的生命?
My life?
如果没有你心爱的女人?
Is there one?
你还能活下去吗?
Without the woman you love within it?
这是我生存的最大动力
I've never had stronger reason to live.
我知道你的心愿 Crixus
I know your heart, Crixus.
我也曾牵挂我此生挚爱
I felt the beating of it within my chest once.
那你该知道 我绝对会存活下来
Then you know I'll fucking survive.
与Naevia重逢
And see Naevia returned to me.
像我妻子与我重逢那样?
As my wife was returned?
Batiatus下令杀了她
Batiatus ordered her death.
你怎么知道的?
How did you come upon this?
是他的走狗Aulus亲口所说
By tongue of his man Aulus,
之后我就送他上西天了
before silencing it forever.
我要亲眼目睹Batiatus家族分崩离析
I will see the House of Batiatus fall,
让整个庄园陷入血海
and with it the villain's blood upon the earth.
我要是你 也会这样的
As would I, in your position.
可我与你不同
But I am far removed.
我逃出去 对Naevia有害无利
My escape would not aid Naevia.
要是我被罗马人追击
How would I purchase her freedom,
我又该怎样为她赎回自由
or even find her,
或是找到她呢?
while being hunted like a dog by the Romans?
加入我们
Join me,
我们一起去寻找她
and we will find her together.
你知道 若在来生
You know that in another life,
我们可能会情如手足的
you and I may have been as brothers.
可这是在今生
But not in this one.
我必须在竞技场上赢得自由
I must win my freedom in the arena.
那我们就是彼此的障碍了
Then we stand in the way of each other's cause.
而我们所做的均是正义之举
And both are just.
可若我倒下
But if I fall,
我要你答应我 去找Naevia
I'd have you swear to find Naevia
并让她恢复自由
and see her freed.
只要你胜利了 我就答应你
And I would have word that if you are victorious,
总有一天 你会手刃Batiatus的
one day you will have Batiatus' life.
那就明天吧
Tomorrow, then.
我们必须死一个
One of us dies.
恐怕注定就是如此
I fear it was always fated so.
主人
Dominus.
你弄到我们明天需要的东西了吗?
Were you able to procure what we need for tomorrow?
老Marcellus总是乐于相助
Good Marcellus was ever helpful.
退下吧
Leave us.
Varro的眼光不错嘛
Varro possessed a fine eye.
谈谈生意的事情吧
Turn yours towards business.
从Marcellus那儿买到了什么?
What has coin extracted from Marcellus?
一个解决麻烦问题的方法
A solution to most vexing problem.
在他杯子里滴上几滴
A few drops in his cup,
就万事大吉了
and fate is sealed.
但是可别把他杀了
It must not kill him.
必须让我们的客人相信 比赛是公平的
Our guests need to believe the match balanced,
以免把事情给搞砸了
lest goodwill turn to accusation.
它只会让Crixus变虚弱
It will but weaken Crixus,
让斯巴达克斯占得上风
allowing Spartacus advantage.
这可真是神奇啊
It is a marvel.
如此微小的东西 却能让一段传奇覆灭
That something so slight could topple a legend.
人总是会倒下的
All men fall.
只是时间和方式不同罢了
It is but time and method that differ.
务必完成
See it done.
这次行动 就是那该死高卢人的死期
And in the act, the end of that fucking Gaul.
Crixus的动作非常犀利啊
Crixus moves with deadly purpose.
他跟斯巴达克斯的表演
He gives much better showing against Spartacus
可比跟蠢Varro的好多了
than the fool Varro.
可怜的Varro啊
Poor Varro.
他根本没有赢的机会 不是吗?
He never stood proper chance, did he?
可Crixus 不管怎样 都能对那战神的头衔和性命
Crixus, however, threatens to strip the champion
构成绝对的威胁
of life and title.
确实如此
Indeed.
高卢人还真令人吃惊
The Gaul yet surprises.
至死方休
To the very end.
恕罪
Apologies.
(当天早晨)
尊贵的Batiatus家族依然谦逊...
The noble House of Batiatus stands humbled...
真是受到了众神早已安排好的
Humbled by the fortunes the gods have seen fit
财运眷顾啊...
to shower upon us...
我觉得应该说是"好运" 吧
I should use "blessings" instead.
"财运" 只能指代钱财
"Fortune" has but connotation of coin.
那就 好运吧
Blessings, then.
哦 Quintus 城里还能有第二个像你这般的男人吗?
Oh, Quintus, has this city yet beheld such a man?
你父亲一定非常骄傲
Your father would be so proud.
那老混蛋肯定会嫉妒死
The old bastard would have cracked with jealously,
我这不足道的儿子 让他黯然失色
to be so eclipsed by unworthy son.
他爱你啊 Quintus
He loved you, Quintus.
但他从没相信过我
Yet he never believed in me.
如果他能活着 看见Batiatus家族在
Would that he were alive to see the House of Batiatus
我的双翼之下崛起 那该多好啊!
soaring beneath the flapping of my wings!
我们的儿子将继承强大的权势!
Our son shall inherit a fucking empire!
又成权势了 是吗?
An empire now, is it?
呃 地基已经建好
Eh, the foundations already laid.
今天我们将筑起大厦!
Today we build upon it!
斯巴达克斯和Crixus!
Spartacus and Crixus!
两位宿敌 将面对生与死的对决!
Hated foes, facing each other in death!
整个国家的人都将无比羡慕
The whole of the Republic shall whisper with envy
这只有少数人才能见证的盛况
what so privileged few bore witness.
它将被永载于史册
It will be a thing not soon forgotten.
我怕你的决心不够啊
I fear your resolve grows soft.
足够了
Stone.
我只是希望能够做个了断
I but wish an end to the matter.
对于他自己也是如此
And to the man himself.
Ashur已经做到了
Ashur already attends to it.
将不幸的过去抛掉
Turn thoughts from unfortunate past,
用将来的荣耀来补偿
and fix on glorious future.
这些庆典会让大家兴奋得发抖
These celebrations can cause hands to tremble.
再老练的人也无法抗拒啊
Even most practiced ones.
非常感谢
Gratitude.
不要紧张
See nerves calmed.
你会做得很好的
You'll do well here.
我能感觉得到
I have a feeling of it.
你被允许和主人坐在一起享用晚餐?
You are allowed to eat from your master's table?
我这是为强大的Crixus与战神决斗之前
I prepare this as a tribute to the mighty Crixus,
对他的一种致敬吧
before his match against the champion.
那么 愿众神保佑他
May the gods bless it, then.
并且赐予他力量 杀掉斯巴达克斯
And give him strength to kill Spartacus.
我可不会瞎祈祷
I would save prayer.
我不认为斯巴达克斯今天就会死
I do not believe Spartacus will fall this day.
我听说Crixus在火神节的竞技场
I have heard Crixus bested him once in the arena,
赢过他一次
at the Vulcanalia.
是什么让你觉得这次
What leads you to certainty
不会出现一样的情况?
against similar outcome?
我们这里的很多事情
I am certain of many things
我都能肯定
within these walls.
你的美丽如此出众
Your beauty among them.
Aurelia啊
Aurelia.
训练场上有人找你
You are needed in the square.
待在我身边
Stay to my side.
不要走开
Do not stray from it,
我想看着你活着出去
and I will see you beyond these walls.
我又不是小孩子了
I do not need you to hold hand.
我只想保护你安全啊 你他妈的傻子!
I only wish your life protected, you fucking cock!
声音再大点 我们都会没命
Speak louder, and see us all undone.
哈 我真想把他该死的鞭子弄走
Ha, I would have his fucking whip removed,
还有那条挥鞭子的臂膀
along with the arm that wields it.
Doctore是个可敬的人
Doctore is an honorable man.
我不想让他死
I would not have him dead.
奴隶也一样
Nor any slave.
你还真悲天悯人啊
You fret of shit and piss.
没有Crixus Rhaskos和其他人
Rhaskos and the others
还是不会死心塌地
still will not fall to purpose without Crixus.
他们会抓住时机的
They will seize the moment.
Crixus死了的话
Crixus is dead,
就只有一位战神了
and there stands but one champion.
Doctore啊
Doctore.
喝水?
Water?
他们庆典一般疏于防范
These celebrations have habit of turning from control.
如果还这样
Should they again,
就搬去安全的地方
remove to a safe place.
不存在安全的地方
None exist.
自从Varro被你亲手杀死之后 就再没有了
Not since Varro was taken from me by your hand.
正因如此 我对这种行径一直鄙视
And I shall forever despise it for the deed.
包括下命令的那个声音
In company with the voice that commanded it.
你在怪Batiatus
You blame Batiatus.
因为很多事情
For many things.
但不是这件
But not this.
是Numerius那小子下令
It was the boy Numerius who demanded
把简单的竞技变成了惨案
simple sport end in death.
那我就该相信一个 为达目的不择手段的人吗?
And I should believe a man that would do anything to win?
不要把我当傻子
Do not take me a fool.
Ashur为Crixus准备了午餐
Ashur prepares meal for Crixus,
还说你必胜无疑
and speaks of the certainty of your fucking victory.
他们在食物下毒?
They corrupt his food?
对Varro不也是一样吗?
Was it the same for Varro?
所以你才能赢他?
Is that how you bested him?
这跟我没关系
I have no hand in this.
即便如此 我还是希望Crixus
Were that true, I would still pray Crixus
能在倒下之前 亲手把你解决了
takes your life before he falls.
你背叛了我
You betrayed me.
但我知道 错
Yet I've come to see that the fault
不在你自己
is not your own.
不能因为你太软弱而责备你
You cannot be blamed for being weak.
所有男人面对诱惑 都一样软弱
All men are, when faced with wet opportunity.
我可以忘却这个
I would put it behind us.
作为回报 我只要真心话
All I ask in return is the truth.
告诉我 Naevia对你毫无意义
Tell me Naevia held no meaning for you.
你要我说假话
You ask me to speak with false tongue.
就当是为了我们的孩子不行吗?
What would it conjure for our child?
孩子?
Child?
木早已成舟
Seed has at last taken hold.
上帝保佑了我们
The gods bless us.
你觉得我是父亲?
You would divine me as father?
不是主人的吗?
Not Dominus?
我感受到战神的血液
I feel the blood of a champion,
在我体内膨胀
swelling inside me.
Crixus 我感受到了你
I feel you, Crixus.
我经常想
I have often dreamt,
过得平淡点 有个孩子
in quiet moments of having a child.
不过 是和Naevia一起
With Naevia.
我们之间也没什么好说的了
There is nothing left between us.
Crixus啊...
Crixus...
我真没想过 会如此收场
I didn't intend for it to end this way.
Crixus开始谢幕
Crixus begins to fade.
正如所有回忆一样
As all memories do.
你变弱了 是因为他们对你下了毒!
You're weakened because they have poisoned you!
干掉他!
Finish him!
他们都希望你死
They wish you dead.
我真不想如此
I would not have this.
加入我吧 兄弟
Join me, brother.
让我们一起见证Batiatus家族的覆灭
And we shall see the House of Batiatus fall.
干掉那条狗!
Kill the dog!
斯巴达克斯
Spartacus.
啊!
Argh!
杀死他们!
Kill them!
一个不留!
Kill them all!
诸位 不要惊慌
Do not be alarmed people.
一切都在我们掌控之中
Everything is under control.
请便吧
Please.
他想杀你啊
He tried to kill you.
那该死的畜生
That fucking animal.
我们必须稳定局势!
We must calm this!
该死的守卫都哪去了?
Where are the fucking guards?
你还站那儿干嘛?
Why do you stand there?
召集你的人马!
Gather your men!
我希望你自己好生保重
I shall see you properly attended.
啊!
Argh!
Hamilcar啊!
Hamilcar!
Crixus啊!
Crixus!
做什么傻事?
What is this madness?
斯巴达克斯给我们指引了道路
Spartacus shows us the way.
他就是条毫无尊严的狗!
He is a dog without honor!
是这个家族毫无尊严!
This house is without honor!
Batiatus处死了他的妻子!
Batiatus ordered his wife dead!
而主人...
And Domina...
她辱没我
She has tainted me,
是因为我刺痛了她的心
because I spur her fucking heart.
我将此生都献给了这训练场!
I have given my life to this ludus!
不 是他们让你变成了奴隶
No, they stole it from you.
我们也是如此
From all of us.
你要我信任你
You asked me to put faith in you.
那你也要信任我
I ask the same.
献身荣耀
Honor us all,
屠灭这肮脏的家族
and see an end of this fucking house.
走吧
Go.
不!
No!
我为你赢取这一刻 兄弟...
I save you this time, brother...
啊!
Ahhh!
朋友们
Friends.
庄园之内 绝对安全
We are perfectly safe inside the villa.
现下形势尚在处理!
The situation is being attended!
你们无需惊慌
Still your hearts.
我的卫兵目前无疑
This very moment my guards are no doubt
正在处理...
dealing with these...
他们都疯了!
They've lost mind!
Ilithyia在他妈哪儿?
Where the fuck is Ilithyia?
跟我来! 我们离开这里!
Come! Let us away!
把门都封上
Seal the doors.
任何人不得从此通过
Let no one beyond them.
那客人们呢?
What of the guests?
我是副将的妻子
I am the wife of the Legatus.
快他妈把门封上!
Seal the fucking doors!
Ilithyia啊!
Ilithyia!
把门打开!
Open the doors!
还记得我在这间屋子
Do you recall what I said
说过什么吗?
in this very room?
我说 如果Barca的离去另有隐情
That if there was more to Barca's departure,
那我们可得好好聊聊了
you and I would share words.
Doctore啊...
Doctore...
你他妈闭嘴
Do not fucking speak.
我看到你们窃窃私语
I have seen you play tongue upon ear,
嘀咕下毒的事
whispering poison.
败坏家族荣耀
Infecting the honor of this house.
你想杀我这样一个手无寸铁的人吗?
You would kill a defenseless man?
这么做有狗屁荣耀可言?
Where is the fucking honor in that?
我倒要看看教给你的 你是否还记得
Let's see if you recall what I taught you.
那时你还算是个男人
When you were yet a man.
门...
The doors...
Glaber副将的手下...
Glaber's men...
把门封上了...
sealed the doors...
是Ilithyia
Ilithyia.
她怎么会做这种事?
Why would she do such a thing?
母亲!
Mother!
Quintus... 走!
Quintus... Go!
快走!
Go!
来啊
Come.
来啊 你们这些罗马贱女
Come here you Roman pussies.
我们都会死的
We are all of us dead.
不 我们家族会东山再起
No. We will regain this House.
带好Numerius 隐蔽起来
Take Numerius, conceal yourselves.
跟我来
Come.
我知道一个地方
I know a place.
你要去哪儿啊?
Where do you go?
去我丈夫那儿
To my husband.
斯巴达克斯真该碎尸万段
And the death of Spartacus.
悲惨至极
Pathetic.
你以为这有何不同吗?
You think this will cause difference?
纵然生命凋零
Even if life fades,
我的双手却依旧强大
my hand shall yet be felt.
Barca之死便是拜它所赐
It plotted the death of Barca.
它见证了行政官命毙黄泉
Saw the Magistrate's end.
甚至迫使Glaber副将掏出了赞助费
It even helped force Glaber to patronage.
这家族的每一分每一寸
Every beam, every stone in this fucking house
都烙有Ashur的印记!
bears the mark of Ashur!
仅烙下了你的背叛
It bears only your treachery.
我他妈背叛?
My fucking treachery?
你什么时候为我Ashur说过话?
When did you stand forth for Ashur?
平日你们谁不对我
When did any of you greet me
冷嘲热讽 嗤之以鼻
short of mockery and scorn,
你们这些狗杂碎!
fucking cunts!
这是你应得的下场!
You received what you deserved!
你们出卖了Barca和其他所有人
For Barca and all the others that you have betrayed,
如今你的死期已致
your time is done.
能让我死在竞技场上吗
Would that this were the arena.
你的血会辱没沙场
Your blood would dishonor the sand.
那就送我上路吧
Send me on my way, then.
让我像角斗士一样死去
As you would a Gladiator.
求你 Doctore
Please, Doctore.
临终前的仁慈...
A parting kindness...
Ashur 你妈的!
Ashur!
Ashur 我操你妈!
Quintus啊...
Quintus...
是Quintus吗?
Quintus?
你说对了
You were right.
你我之间 还有事情尚未解决
There is still something between you and I.
Naevia在哪儿?
Where is Naevia?
在哪儿?
Where?!
带我和主人离开庄园
See me and the Dominus out of the villa
我就告诉你
and I will tell you.
我不相信你
I do not believe you.
求你...
Please...
Crixus啊...
Crixus...
我们的孩子...
our child...
我宁可看着他死掉
I would rather see it dead,
也不愿意看你为他哺乳
than suckle your breast.
我们必须藏起来...
We must conceal ourselves...
就是你下的令吧?
Was it yours?
那细小的声音
That small, little voice.
正是那样的轻声细语 就夺走了
Did it form the words that robbed Varro
Varro的生命吗?
of his life?
你说Varro?!
Varro?!
他本就该死!
He deserved to die!
他什么也不是!
He was nothing!
你知道他什么?
What did you know of the man?
你知道他可以 为臂弯里入睡的孩子
That he would sing to his child,
轻轻唱出摇篮曲吗?
sleeping in his arms?
当我情绪不佳时
Or kiss the tears from my cheek,
他会吻去我颊边的泪水?
when I was of a mood?
你知道父亲的含义吗?
Did you know the father?
丈夫的责任吗?
The husband?
他不是一个完美的人
He was not a perfect man.
但他是我的男人
But he was mine.
他是我的!
He was mine!
呀!
Yaaa!
他是我的!
He was mine!
我的! 我的!
Mine! Mine!
啊!
Ahhh!
他是我的
He was mine.
呀!
Yaaa!
我的...
Mine...
Aurelia啊...
Aurelia...
别激动
Be still.
结束了
It's done.
照看下这个女孩
Look to the girl.
这还不够吗?
Is this not enough?
还要死多少人?
How many more must die?
我只想看一个人死
I would see but one.
我是你们的主人!
I am your Dominus!
我要把你们该死的黑心肠都挖出来!
I will have your fucking hearts!
Quintus啊...
Quintus...
Lucretia啊!
Lucretia!
你想做什么?
What would you do?
再次将妻子拥入怀中?
To hold your wife again?
再次感受她肌肤的温度?
To feel the warmth of her skin?
她双唇的味道?
The taste of her lips?
你还要杀多少人?
How many men would you kill?
一百?
A hundred?
一千?
A thousand?
只有一人
There stands but one,
横亘在你和她之间
between you and her.
去找她吧
Go to her.
告诉她 就算是天神自己
Tell her the gods themselves
也不能将你们分开
would not keep you apart.
撒谎!
Lie!
就像你说我妻子的谎话一样
As you lied to me of my wife.
Oenemaus啊...
Oenemaus...
你在我面前什么也不是!
You were nothing before me!
我给了你一切!
I gave you everything!
我给你出路 让你接受自己命运!
I gave you the means to accept your fate!
现在 你将被命运所毁灭
And now you are destroyed by it.
我做这件事
I have done this thing
是为了正义
because it is just.
血债血偿
Blood demands blood.
我们活着 却很困惑 长久以来
We have lived and lost,
一直被主人的反复无常所羁绊
at the whims of our masters for too long.
我不会再任其继续
I would not have it so.
我不愿意再看到 为了娱乐的目的
I would not see the passing of a brother
而牺牲掉自己的兄弟
for the purpose of sport.
我不愿意再看到 毫无因由 就挖出别人的心脏
I would not see another heart ripped from chest,
或随意致人死地
or breath forfeit for no cause.
我知道 并不是你们所有人都希望如此
I know not all of you wished this.
但是已经做了
Yet it is done.
都结束了
It is done.
你们的性命在自己手里
Your lives are your own.
各走各路...
Forge your own path...
或者加入我们
or join with us,
我们一起 震撼整个罗马
and together we shall see Rome tremble.